Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ע"ח, Ayin Chet,
78.
And we begin a new פרק, perek, the eighth פרק, perek, האשה
שנפלו. Haishah Shenafelu. And as opposed to some of the previous פרקים,
perakim, which had to do with the what are called like you
know what's like the ongoing the תנאי כתובה, tenai ketubah, the reciprocal
obligations of husband and wife and if you would like lived marriage,
what people's responsibilities are, what happens if they're not living up to
their responsibilities, what happens if there is you know tension in the
marriage, there are vows that are obstacles, there are somebody says you
know I wasn't expecting this type of a wife, I wasn't expecting
this type of a husband, מומים, mumim, all these types of issues
which leads to questions about do you force a divorce, do you
divorce without a כתובה, ketubah, with a כתובה, ketubah, you know very
like real live stuff about the nature of the marriage. Now we
turn more to the issue of like the financial aspects of it
and the husband's entitlement in terms to the פירות. perot. You might
remember that one of the הלכות halachot of the כתובה, ketubah, one
of the תנאי כתובה tenai ketubah is that he eats the fruit
of the wife's property. So in the case where we're talking about
land that's like literal, she comes in with property in her name
that is not the dowry. The dowry is stuff that the title
gets transferred to him. It's a very specific amount that's listed in
the כתובה, ketubah, right she brings it in, that's called נכסי צאן
ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. By the way, we're not talking about the
dowry. We're talking about property that she happens to have in
her name
and that one of the הלכות halachot is that he gets any
income off of that property. So it's not mentioned in the כתובה,
ketubah, she retains title. Okay, now in the case and that's called
פירות. perot. So in the time of, you know it could be
extremely literal, right, it could be that you know she got fields
and that the yield of the fields that goes to him. Of
course, he would have to pay the expenses or whatever. He would
get the net, he wouldn't get the gross. But it could be
that she owns you know buildings, houses, apartments and he gets the
rent, that you know that rental properties. It could be that she's
got a nice 401k, well that's retirement or whatever. Anyway, she's got
a nice investment account and he gets the dividends. Okay, so that's
the בעל אוכל פירות baal ochel perot and that's the aspect that
we are going to focus on now because you would think he
gets the rights to the fruit, to the benefit, but she retains
title. So is she allowed now while she's married to sell that
property to somebody else? Okay, right that's an right if she has
the right to the פירות, perot, can she sell that let's say
rental property or those fields to someone else because she still has
the title? So that's the initial focus of our משנה. mishnah. So
let's take a look.
Is נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel and the נדוניה nidunyah the
same general term? Yes.
נכסי צאן ברזל,
Nichsei
tzon
barzel, the נדוניה nidunyah is נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. Okay,
but you're talking about נכסי מלוג. nichsei milog. נכסי מלוג Nichsei milog
which are not listed in the כתובה, ketubah, they don't need to
be listed. It's because they're not transferred. She retains title. Right, that's
what we're talking about. Yes, we're talking about נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog,
okay, which is the basic default status of any property that she
owns that she brings into the you know that she has in
her name you know when they get married. Yes.
נכסי צאן ברזל Nichsei tzon barzel just goes directly to the husband,
but he has to give it back to her.
He has to give it back. The value is written in the
כתובה ketubah and if they get divorced or he you know or
he dies before her then you know then she gets it back,
right. If she dies he inherits her but then the her if
she has children and he has children from another wife then it
passes on specifically to her children, etc. Right. האשה שנפלו לה נכסים,
Haishah shenafelu lah nechasim,
so a woman had property literally fell to her, which like she
inherited. So it fell to a woman. Well, she inherited she inherited
property because the assumption is like where does a woman get property,
like you know she's not going out and earning it or whatever.
That's the assumption, but she can inherit property. Okay, so somehow another
she has property in her name, it fell to her, she inherited
it let's say. When did she inherit it? When did it when
did it become her property? עד שלא תתארס, Ad shelo titaras, if
it was before even the אירוסין, erusin, the קידושין, kiddushin, so when
there was not even any husband in sight anywhere. So in this
case מודים בית שמאי ובית הלל, Modim Beit Shammai veBeit Hillel, both
agree שמוכרת ונותנת וקיים. shemocheres venosanes vekayam. She can לכתחילה lechatichilah sell
that property,
of course, and it's a valid sale. Okay, and presumably that means
she can sell it even after אירוסין. erusin. Okay, because why could
אירוסין erusin matter? Right, all these הלכות halachot really kick in at
the time of נישואין. nissuin. Okay, so she got the property before
אירוסין. erusin. Presumably now there's been קידושין kiddushin but no נישואין, nissuin,
so the husband yet isn't entitled, but he's on the scene, but
it doesn't matter. She can still go ahead and sell that property.
Why not? Now משנתארסה, mishenitarsah, let's say the property fell to her
after the קידושין kiddushin before his נישואין. nissuin. Okay, and there's no
נישואין. nissuin. Now in this case again he doesn't yet have rights
to it, but the difference is is that when she got that
title he was already on the scene. We were already could already
look into our crystal
ball. And see they'll probably wind up getting נישואין, Nisu'in, most אירוסין
Eirusin leads to נישואין, Nisu'in, and he'll probably, and then when it
is, he'll have the right to the fruits from this property. So
should she be allowed, she got this property after the קידושין, Kiddushin,
so he's got his eye, so he already, they're already in a
marriage context, should she be allowed to sell it and deprive him
of the future possibility to get the פירות? peirot? Maybe legally she's
entitled, they're not yet even נשואה, nesu'ah, so she has a hundred
percent rights, but still there's a sense of should she be allowed
to. What's what does the future hold?
It's hard to understand why she shouldn't.
Why she shouldn't.
I understand. I understand. No, so it's not a legal issue, it's
more well, see. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, תמכור timkor לכתחילה,
lechatchila, she can sell it. Why not? It's her property, they're not
yet נשואים. nesu'im. Before נישואין. Nisu'in. ובית הלל אומרים, u'Veit Hillel omrim,
לא תמכור. lo timkor. No, לכתחילה lechatchila
she shouldn't sell it because as I said, no, there's not a
legal problem of selling it, but it's not appropriate. She got it
once she was already married to this guy. There was already קידושין,
Kiddushin, once he was already expecting, oh good, I'll be in expectation,
it wouldn't be appropriate. אבל אלו ואלו מודים, Aval elu ve'elu modim,
שאם מכרה ונתנה קיים, she'im machra v'natna kayam, that if she sold
it, it's binding because they're not yet נשואים, nesu'im, he doesn't have
any rights to this property yet. Okay, so that's if she got
the property and sold it before the נישואין. Nisu'in. Now, אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehudah, אמרו חכמים לפני רבן גמליאל, amru Chachamim lifnei
Rabban Gamliel, the sages said to Rabban Gamliel, הואיל וזכה באשה לא
יזכה בנכסים? ho'il v'zacha b'ishah lo yizkeh b'nechasim?
Since he basically merited, or the word זוכה zocheh also means זכות,
zechut, since he has legal rights, since he actually acquired is the
sense, the woman, should he not also acquire her property? So what
he is basically saying is that this gets obviously to issues that
we've seen before, but really issues of מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, how
much the idea of אירוסין Eirusin and קידושין, Kiddushin, קנין כספו, kinyan
kaspo, you give כסף kesef and so on, how much the wife
is considered property of the husband. And it seems to be what
the חכמים Chachamim are saying to Rabban Gamliel is like look, I
get that he doesn't get the קנין פירות, kinyan peirot, he doesn't
get the פירות peirot until נישואין, Nisu'in, like that's part of the
lived relationship, they're living together, he's providing for her, so he's providing
for her, he gets the interest, the income off of her property.
But shouldn't he, even at the time of קידושין, Kiddushin, have some
type of monetary ownership over her property? Even though the things like
I get said the obligation, he provides food, sex, clothing, he gets
the income, that's the lived relationship, that's נישואין. Nisu'in. But what do
you have before נישואין? Nisu'in? קידושין. Kiddushin. What's קידושין? Kiddushin? A type
of an ownership of the woman, if you conceptualize it as that
way. So if it's an ownership of the woman, shouldn't it also
be an ownership of her property? And therefore she shouldn't be allowed
to sell it even before נישואין. Nisu'in. Maybe he doesn't yet get
the פירות, peirot, but if he has rights, legal rights to the
woman, that's what קידושין Kiddushin is, a type of an ownership, he
should have legal rights to her property.
He has zero obligations. He doesn't have any.
I understand, but that's the argument. I think it's an interesting way
of framing it of sort of think like, they're not disputing the
sense of obligations and the lived relationship that kicks in at the
נישואין, Nisu'in, but they're saying there's a concept of קנין kinyan that
exists already now. And if that קנין kinyan applies to the woman,
shouldn't it also apply to her property and limit her right to
sell the property? Yeah. Wait, wait, wait, now hold on.
Does
her age have anything to do with these considerations?
No, why should her age be relevant?
Well, if she were a minor, then would she have the right
to sell anything to begin with?
Oh, you're right. Meaning she could not, that's a good point. Right,
she has to be at least twelve years old or else there's
a discussion about at what age the rabbis sort of allow people
to sell property. Real estate also they were stricter about than they
were about non-real estate. So if we're not necessarily talking about real
estate, although that's the classic case, but if it is real estate,
then yeah, she'd have to be בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, so she'd
have to be a נערה. na'arah. If it were like other things,
let's say it was an investment account, well you don't sell an
investment account, but anyway, if it were a car, she rented out
a car and earned income off of a car, then she would
be able to do it even younger than בת מצוה bat mitzvah
they get, the rabbis allowed her to. But you're right, you need
to assume that she's of a legal age that she can do
a sale. Yeah.
Why not take that argument to an extreme? Let him have full
rights and sell it. I mean if he זוכה zocheh in the
woman, let him be זוכה zocheh in everything, let him go and
sell it.
Right. So it's an interesting balance, and he's not זוכה zocheh in
the woman completely, meaning the קנין kinyan of אשה, ishah, he can't
go ahead and sell her as a slave, he can't go ahead
and sell her to somebody else as a wife. Exactly. But there's
a concept of קנין, kinyan, and he said that concept of קנין
kinyan should be enough to give him some ownership of the property
and prevent her from selling the property. Right.
I wanted to push on that.
What לא יזכה בנכסים? lo yizkeh b'nechasim? Shouldn't he have legal rights
to the property? What legal rights does he really have with this
woman? He can't have sex with her.
Well, he can biblically, meaning if you ask, I mean look this
gets us into מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, so I'll just say one
thing about this now. But if you ask what is... If if
קידושין Kiddushin is a biblical is a קניין kinyan concept an ownership
concept to what degree does he own her? I mean he doesn't
have rights to her מעשה ידיה ma'aseh yadeha that's all rabbinic. So
the real answer is you know you know how he owns her?
He owns her as sexual property. That he is because the reason
we learned that the husband has an obligation to have sex with
his wife and if he doesn't he's a מורד mored but we
also learned and that's the מצות עונה. mitzvat onah. We also learned
she's obligated to have sex with him and if she doesn't she's
a מורדת. moredet. We never spelled out exactly where her obligation to
have sex with her husband comes from right? She doesn't have a
מצות עונה mitzvat onah and the simple sense is and the רמב"ם
Rambam says this although although the ר"ש Rash disagrees, the ר"ש Rash
wants to make it a parallel to עונה onah but the רמב"ם
Rambam basically says she's his property, his sexual property and that's why
he's entitled to have sex with her, okay? And that led to
a whole interesting discussion about like marital rape and how forbidden marital
rape was and so on, you know obviously it was forbidden as
a morally and ethically but it was was it really considered like
a type of a you know anyway there's like very important discussion
around that okay?
So well we won't get to all of it but I'm sure
we'll revisit you know because that's a larger discussion not all rooted
in the גמרא Gemara but that's anyway but that's something to keep
in mind. So that's what the חכמים Chachamim say to רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel even at the time of קידושין Kiddushin aren't you glad
you asked even at the time of קידושין Kiddushin he should not
be able he should not be she should not be able to
sell because he should have rights to the property even from the
time of קידושין. Kiddushin. So אמר להם amar lahem רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel said back to them על חדשים אנו בושים al chadashim anu
boshim we're embarrassed about the new property that she gets property that
she gets after נישואין Nisuin you know and and that becomes hers
after נישואין Nisuin and that we say a sale is not valid
and we're embarrassed about that rule so this is her property so
you know where did the rabbis come off saying that the sale
that she makes on it is not valid? So and we're embarrassed
about that ruling אלא שאתם מגלגלים עלינו את הישנים ela she'atem megalgelin
aleinu et hayeshanim you want to now roll into this and say
that he's not even entitled to sell the old property? The property
that she had even from before the נישואין? Nisuin? So it's basically
it's almost like a moral response. It's like you know this whole
thing feels inappropriate.
They want to change it.
Okay so obviously it's not completely wrong and we'll see why you
know but there's an acknowledgment bottom line is this is her property
and it's problematic enough to say that she can't sell it after
the נישואין. Nisuin. Don't start with me before the נישואין. Nisuin. Okay
which is again not exactly a legal response but it's a sort
of a deep sort of you know moral response. Okay but there
is a legal response element to it too. It's her property! You're
wrong. It's not his property, it's her property. Even the stuff she
gets after נישואין Nisuin is her property. Okay. So that's stuff she
sells before נישואין. Nisuin. נפלו לה משנישאת. naflu lah misheniset.
Now let's say she got the property became she inherited the property
after נישואין Nisuin okay. So now he's entitled to the פירות peirot
and now so it's when he does have legal rights to it.
But the question is does that legal right mean that she's not
allowed to sell it? Okay נפלו לה משנישאת naflu lah misheniset and
I'll discuss so what in a minute but let's just read the
משנה. Mishna. נפלו לה משנישאת naflu lah misheniset אלו ואלו מודים elu
v'elu modim then בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
both agree שאם מכרה ונתנה שהבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות she'im machra v'natna
shehaba'al motzi miyad halakochot that in that case it's not binding. She
got the property after נישואין Nisuin when she was in a context
where he had legal rights to the property she got it and
she tries to sell it it's not binding. Now what did she
try to sell? We will see in the גמרא Gemara what you
might you know that you there's two things she could have tried
to sell right now. She got this rental property she got this
apartment okay and she tried to sell it to somebody else and
the husband can take it away from the people she sold it
to. What did she try to sell? One scenario is she tried
to sell the actual property itself that's what it sounds like. Okay
then that's a חידוש chiddush because even though the husband is entitled
to the income he she has the title to the property why
should she not be able to sell it to somebody else? Maybe
it'll be a valid sale and he can still collect the income
during the interim of the marriage but why should she not be
able to transfer title? Okay so that's a really good question now
you understand the point אנו בושים anu boshim we're embarrassed right? Why
should she not be able to transfer title even though the husband
is entitled to the income? That the other possibility is not that
she tried to sell the the title itself but she tried to
transfer the husband's rights the the right to the income. So what
I basically did is I sold to you David there I sold
to you I didn't sell to you my apartment I sold to
you the rights of the the rental rights I assumed you could
do this for 10 years but I retain the title. So there
you can understand why that's much more obvious that the wife shouldn't
be able to do that because the husband is the one that
has the rights to the income why should I be able to
sell the rights of the income to somebody else? Okay so we'll
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Joe, yes.
So
if the husband married her when she had property
so maybe he married her because she has property and so she
cannot sell it because she's married?
Right. Right.
Right, so that might be part of the reason why that if
she gets the property before the נישואין Nissuin that he, that she
shouldn’t sell it because that was part of his
expectation, that's part of it, yeah.
Or since it’s in רמבם Rambam mostly in הלכות אישות, Hilchot Ishut,
it sounds like he’s getting that part back. It sounds like she
tries to sell the title, and sounds like she, that he’s taking
the title back, and that would make sense why רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, why it’s a חידוש chiddush and why רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says אנו בושים, anu boshim, we’re embarrassed,
because logically you would think she should be able to, and that’s
the חידוש. chiddush. So I agree, the simple sense of the משנה
mishna she’s trying to transfer the title, and the חידוש chiddush is
that once he has rights to the
פירות, perot, that allows, that prevents her from transferring even the title.
Is this the same issue of whether קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי?
kinyan perot k'kinyan haguf dami?
It might be related, yes, and that, yes, and we’ll get to
that, touch on that in the גמרא, gemara, yes.
And בושים, boshim, does that come from בשי? bushai? Do you often
see the Rabbis say that?
Yeah, it's a good question. I mean, it is really interesting, right?
And particularly you know, if you look at it like from like
a feminist perspective, you know, the whole מסכת, masechet, right? It’s always
men who are sort of legislating for women. Now dominantly, I will
say, I mean, it’s an interesting question what sort of how all
of you are leaving sort of, you know, the whole impression of
learning through מסכת כתובות. Masechet Ketubot. Do you leave with a feeling
like, yeah, you know, they're talking about the woman's body and they're
using all these, you know, objectifying and these metaphors and so on,
which is true, but at the same time so much of the
מסכת masechet and you know, and so much of what כתובות Ketubot
is about is about protecting the woman’s interest, right? And making all
of these rules in order to protect the wife's interest. So, you
know, you don't get an automatic societal shift about how men sort
of looked and conceptualized, you know, about women happening overnight, and some
of those things are certainly there, you know, but my basic sort
of takeaway sort of, you know, impression, you know, feeling about it
is that it's, that it’s amazing how much the Rabbis, you know,
how much was done here to legislate to protect the woman's interest
while there are definitely challenging segments of the מסכת. masechet. So the
word בושים boshim like as a reflection of, you know, a self-awareness
of, here you have men legislating for women and things that are,
you know, being aware of things that are problematic and using that
phrase בושים, boshim, right? Is that specifically related to the male, you
know, the men and the women aspect? There, the men and they
know that if they’re doing a, passing legislation that benefits the husband,
which is what they’re doing, right? They’re saying the husband has rights
to stop the wife's sale, that there is some sense about being
embarrassed about that, where they wouldn’t say it if it was something
that was, you know, maybe problematic but didn’t have this sense about
men legislating for women. So I do wonder about that. I don't
know where, you know, I haven't checked where else it occurs in
the Tannaitic literature, but we can certainly check for that, yeah.
In general, can a person structure a contract of sale such that
he sell the title but not the פירות? perot? Like if I’m
going to sell you my car but you can't use
it, is that קנין פירות? kinyan perot? No, that’s the opposite. גוף
מהיום ופירות לאחר מיתה. Guf mehayom u'perot l'achar mita. You know, you
can do that. You can split the title from the פירות perot
and sell one without the other.
Why couldn’t she, why couldn't she potentially sell the title but retain
the, the husband retains rights for the פירות? perot? He could, she
could. And then that would be particularly a חידוש chiddush that even
with that he could be מוציא מיד הלקוחות. motzi miyad halakochot. So
that’s what’s not clear in the משנה. mishna. Okay, so let's keep
on going. It says like this.
Okay, so אלו ואלו מודים, eilu v'eilu modim, אלו ואלו מודים שאם
מכרה ונתנה שבאו הלקוחות. eilu v'eilu modim she'im machra v'natna sheba'u halakochot.
Now, now here’s the another more like complex case. עד שלא נישאת,
ad shelo nisset, she got the property before the נישואין, Nissuin, meaning
at the time of אירוסין. eirusin. So she got it at the
time after קידושין kiddushin before נישואין. Nissuin. We learned already that and
she sold it, it’s valid. בית הלל Beit Hillel says לכתחילה lechatchila
don’t sell, but if she sold it before the נישואין Nissuin it’s
valid. Now what happens if she got it after קידושין kiddushin and
then now there was נישואין? Nissuin? So you and I would think
that once there's נישואין, Nissuin, once he has his rights, what difference
did it make when she got the property? But maybe not. Maybe
since she had that property independent of him, even though there was
קידושין, kiddushin, there wasn’t נישואין, Nissuin, so she had this before he
had any legal rights, maybe she retains a stronger position in this
property even after the נישואין. Nissuin. So that’s the question. She got
it before the נישואין Nissuin and now there's
נישואין. Nissuin. עד שלא נישאת ונישאת. ad shelo nisset v'nisset. רבן גמליאל
אומר, אם מכרה ונתנה קיים. Rabban Gamliel omer im machra venatna kayam,
בדיעבד b'diavad it's good. Okay, maybe לכתחילה lechatchila she shouldn't sell, that
goes back to the בית הלל Beit Hillel position, but if she
started with this property before the נישואין, Nissuin, she retains rights. The
only time he can stop the sale is if she got the
property after the
נישואין. Nissuin. אמר רבי חנינה בן עקביא, Amar Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya,
Rabbi Chananya, אמר רבי חנינה בן עקביא Amar Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya
said: אמרו לפני חכמים, amru lifnei chachamim, so they presumably again the
Sages said, אמרו לפני רבן גמליאל, amru lifnei Rabban Gamliel, they the
Sages presumably said to
רבן גמליאל: Rabban Gamliel: הואיל וזכה באשה לא יזכה בנכסים? ho'il v'zacha
b'isha lo yizke b'nechasim? If he married, if he has rights in
the woman, doesn’t he have rights in the property? And here, it’s
if you understand it's a stronger argument. Now there’s נישואין. Nissuin. Now
he’s entitled to the פירות. perot. And now he has other rights,
you know, with his wife: מעשה ידיה, ma'aseh yadeha, he has all...
those ongoing נישואין nisuin types of rights. But more to the point,
he has מעשה, maaseh, he has פירות. peiros. So shouldn't that stop
the sale? So אמר להם, amar lahem, he said back to them,
על החדשים אנו בושים. al hachadashim anu boshim. We're embarrassed about the
new stuff, meaning the property that he admits she can't sell is
property she got after the נישואין. nisuin. That's the newest property, the
one she got after the נישואין. nisuin. We're embarrassed about the new
property, property she got after the נישואין nisuin that she's not able
to sell it. אלא שאתם מגלגלים עלינו הישנים? ella she'atem megalgelim aleinu
hayeshanim? You now want to apply it even to the old property,
property she came into the marriage with? Okay, so there's two versions
or maybe two occurrences of this debate. One is they tried to
claim she shouldn't even be able to sell it at the time
of the קידושין, kiddushin, which is a really, you know, extreme argument.
And he said, give me a break, it's bad enough נישואין. nisuin.
And here, though, it's a more limited argument: she shouldn't be able
to sell it if she came into the marriage with it once
they're now נישואין. nisuin. And he says, no, no, no, it's bad
enough that she can't sell the stuff that she got after the
נישואין. nisuin. Don't try to extend this to stuff that she got
before the נישואין nisuin that she brought into the marriage. Let's just
finish—okay, so we'll figure that out. Let's go...
but it would work. He's only saying בדיעבד bedieved it works. אם
מכרה. im makhrah. He doesn't say לכתחילה. lechatchilah.
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you're not לכתחילה lechatchilah allowed, but they
both agree that בדיעבד bedieved it works. Okay, so it's consistent. He
says אם מכרה קיים. im makhrah kayam. Okay, now the משנה Mishnah
ends by saying רבי שמעון חולק
בין נכסים לנכסים.
Rabbi Shimon cholek bein
nechasim lenechasim. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon distinguished between the paper property. נכסים
הידועים לבעל, nechasim hayeduim labaal, if there's property that the husband knows
about, לא תמכור, lo timkor, לכתחילה lechatchilah she can't sell. ואם מכרה
ונתנה בטל. ve'im makhrah venasnah batel. I don't know, the גמרא Gemara
will discuss how you identify what does it mean knows about or
not knows about. And if she sold it, it's null and void,
presumably after the נישואין. nisuin. שאין ידועים לבעל, she'ein yeduim labaal, if
she's got some secret, you know, Swiss bank account or something, something
the husband doesn't know about, לא תמכור, lo timkor, and now it's
the נישואין, nisuin, she should not sell.
ואם מכרה ונתנה קיים, ve'im makhrah venasnah kayam, בדיעבד bedieved it's valid.
And so this goes to your point, because if he doesn't know
about it, he can't speak about having had any expectations about it.
Okay, which but again it's pretty interesting because even if he doesn't
know about it, presumably he's still entitled to the פירות. peiros. But
since he didn't have any reasonable expectations about it, then בדיעבד bedieved
the sale is valid. So very strange. Whether נישואין nisuin or whatever?
This is after the נישואין. nisuin. So that's very strange that that
should make a legal difference whether he knows about it or doesn't
know about it.
It's to your point about, here's an example where the emotional quality
of the relationship in some way informs the
legal accessibility.
Right, that somehow the legal question
about the property is related to somehow some reality of their actual
expectations and their relationship.
Yeah, if she sold it and received financial remuneration. She has money
now. Yeah, who does that money belong to? Does it belong just
to her?
If she has money from
the secret property.
The secret property. It belongs to her. And presumably, though, he gets
the פירות. peiros. It's just that she's like allowed to sell it.
The secret property. Presumably we're not debating that he's still entitled to
the פירות. peiros. Presumably. Presumably the only question is whether if she
sells it can she transfer it or not. Okay, but presumably he's
still entitled to the פירות. peiros. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. So she makes investments like in modern
terms.
He's always going to get the
interest or he's going
to
get the income. Right, exactly. Okay. מאי שנא רישא דלא פליגי ומאי
שנא סיפא דפליגי? mai shena reisha delo pligi u'mai shena seifa depligi?
So why is it in the beginning בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis
Hillel veBeis Shammai don't disagree—wait a minute—it is a
פלוגתא? plugta? Wait
a minute. Yeah, yeah, why is it, why is it in the
first case בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel veBeis Shammai don't disagree
when she basically started with the property before the קידושין? kiddushin? And
then she got married, everybody agrees לכתחילה lechatchilah she can sell it?
And why do they debate when she got the property after the
קידושין? kiddushin? Either way she's selling it before the נישואין. nisuin. What
difference does it make whether she got the property before the קידושין
kiddushin or after the קידושין? kiddushin? So אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, amri
devei Rabbi Yannai, says the house of Rabbi Yannai says, רישא בזכותה
נפלו. reisha bizchutah naflu. In the beginning, when she got the property,
she inherited the property, that was all due to her, right? So
therefore the husband wasn't, she wasn't even engaged or married or whatever,
it was all hers. So she has a hundred percent right. So
even after the קידושין, kiddushin, she לכתחילה lechatchilah can go ahead and
sell it. סיפא, seifa, but in the end, she got the property
after the קידושין, kiddushin, before the נישואין, nisuin, בזכותו נפלו. bizchuto naflu.
Maybe she got it out of his merit. Now this sounds like
we're arguing, right? This sounds like a very non-legal point. Right? It
sounds like we're sort of arguing like, you know, like, oh, why
did you win the lottery? You won the lottery, why'd you get
a big inheritance from your long-lost uncle? Well, since it happened after
your marriage, maybe it was thanks to your husband. That merit allowed
you to get this nice windfall. Well, that מעשה maaseh you're gonna
ask that too. And therefore that gives him some rights. It's a
very
bizarre— So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes from it. We'll
stick with that for now, but then we'll see where the גמרא
Gemara goes from it. So the
גמרא Gemara says סיפא בזכותו נפל, Seifa bizchuto nafal, in the end
after if she got it after קידושין, kiddushin, it was because of
his merit. גמרא Gemara says one minute, אם בזכותו נפל, im bizchuto
nafal, if it was really because of his merit and therefore maybe
like he has rights to it, כי מכרה ונתנה מאי קיים, ki
machra venatna mai kayam, then בדיעבד bedi'avad it shouldn't be good. And
we do agree that בדיעבד bedi'avad it's good before the נישואין. nisu'in.
אלא, Ela, rather say the following. רישא ודאי בזכותה נפל. Reisha vadai
bizchuta nafal. In the beginning when she got it before the marriage,
before the קידושין, kiddushin, it was all due to her and therefore
she can even לכתחילה lechatchila sell it. סיפא, Seifa, in the end,
meaning after the קידושין kiddushin before the נישואין, nisu'in, אימור בזכותה אימור
בזכותו. eimar bizchuta eimar bizchuto. Why did she win the lottery after
the קידושין? kiddushin? Maybe it was her merit, maybe it was his
merit. So therefore they both have, technically she owns it, but he
might have, it might be a little bit thanks to him. And
therefore since it could be partly thanks to him, לכתחילה לא תמכור,
lechatchila lo timkor, she shouldn't sell it because he could say, "Hey
you know, the only reason you got this was because of me."
But one minute, but so that's enough for him to object לכתחילה,
lechatchila, but bottom line you know, she might have gotten it for
her own merit and bottom line she does own it, so אם
מכרה ונתנה קיים, im machra v'natna kayam. בדיעבד bedi'avad it's good. Now
read this way it seems like I said, very strange. Whose merit?
What? Like I mean, we're trying to read like why things happen
in the world? What does that matter in terms of technically who
owns it? So רש"י Rashi reframes it. רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi
says the following, אימור בזכותו, eimar bizchuto,
it's right near the line above where it
says הגהות
מהרי"ל אנדא Hagahot Mahari Landau if you see that, okay. בזכותו, bizchuto,
let's start with בזכותו, bizchuto, כבר זכה בה ובנכסיה. Kvar zachah bah
uvenichaseha.
So רש"י Rashi doesn't mean בזכותו bizchuto means because of his
merit she got a inheritance. It means he was already in the
picture. He already had certain rights to her and to her property.
רש"י Rashi is translating the word זכות zechut into a legal
point, okay, into
a financial point, right, something like רשות. reshut. And look at the
answer, אימור בזכותה אימור בזכותו. eimar bizchuta eimar bizchuto. And how about
the answer in the end, maybe it was his merit, maybe it
was hers. Here's what רש"י Rashi says it means. דאירוסין עושה ספק
נישואין. De'eirusin oseh sefek nisu'in. אירוסין Eirusin makes doubtful נישואין. nisu'in. Now
it's not really doubtful נישואין, nisu'in, but it means the possibility of
נישואין nisu'in is on the horizon. שמא תבוא לידי נישואין שמא לא
תבוא. Shema tavo lidei nisu'in shema lo tavo.
Maybe it will lead to נישואין, nisu'in, maybe not. Now what does
that have to do with whose merit it is? So רש"י Rashi
isn't reading merit to mean merit. רש"י Rashi is reading it as
like once she got the property and they were already had קידושין,
kiddushin, then he could say look, you know, I נישואין nisu'in is
in the offing, we're expecting to get married, you got this property
in the context of a קידושין, kiddushin, and the context of a
קידושין kiddushin when you were already my wife you got this property
and that and what was the natural progression from being קידושין kiddushin
was נישואין, nisu'in, and when we're נישואין nisu'in I'm going to have
rights to the פירות, peirot, and you got it as my wife,
so that should give me the right to object to you selling
it because it sort of, you know, we got it as a
couple, okay, we got it once we were already legally a couple.
And even though I didn't yet have legal rights to the פירות,
peirot, that was the next stage. So that's the fact that you
got it as when we're already a couple should give me a
certain type of a right to say I don't want you to
sell it, okay. So he's translating this idea of זכות zechut as
not like whose merit did she get this big inheritance from, but
he's translating it as like the husband's got some type of a
claim. He's got some type of a right because he's already in
the picture, okay.
It
seems
like it's a ספק, safek, אימור בזכותה אימור בזכותו. eimar bizchuta eimar
bizchuto. Right, so it's a ספק, safek, meaning I wouldn't say it's
a ספק safek as much as like it's a gray, okay. She's
basically still her own legal entity and fundamentally obviously it's her property,
but it's like a gray area, they're not yet נישואין nisu'in but
they're in the partial leading up to the נישואין nisu'in and they're
already a couple. So that might give him enough of a position
to object and to say make some type of a claim, okay.
I mean, you know, I don't know, this is a very loose
analogy and maybe I shouldn't make it, but you know, it gets
to all the questions about like, you know, the husband's paternity rights
if they're not married and whatever, and at what
stage are you in the picture enough that you have some right
to be saying something about it or not. So anyway, so that
seems to be the issue, okay. So that's why even though it's
before נישואין, nisu'in, and even though of course it's still her property
and בדיעבד bedi'avad she can sell it, if she got it once
they were already a couple, he might have a right to say
I don't want you to sell it and to object and maybe
that's enough לכתחילה lechatchila that she shouldn't. Okay, now we go on.
אמר רב יהודה אמרו לפני רבן גמליאל. Amar Rav Yehuda amru lifnei
Rabban Gamliel. They said to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So here's where
the sages, the חכמים Chachamim said she shouldn't even be able to
sell it at the time of קידושין kiddushin because he already has
some because he already owns her. He owns her at the time
of קידושין, kiddushin, then he should own the property and she shouldn't
be able to sell it even then. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya l'hu. They
raised the following question. רבי יהודה לכתחילה או בדיעבד? Rabbi Yehuda l'chatchila
o b'diavad?
When רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is describing this debate between רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel and the חכמים, chachamim,
are the חכמים chachamim trying to say that
לכתחילה l'chatchila she shouldn't be able to sell and they're sort of
arguing against בית שמאי Beit Shammai in favor of בית הלל? Beit
Hillel? Of course,
why would you have to argue against בית שמאי Beit Shammai in
favor of בית הלל? Beit Hillel? Or are they trying to say
בדיעבד b'diavad it shouldn't be valid, which it sounds more like, and
that's what the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say. So let's take a
look. תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, דתניא, detanya, it's spelled
out in a תוספתא, Tosefta, in a ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי יהודה
אמר לפני רבן גמליאל. Amar Rabbi Yehuda amar lifnei Rabban Gamliel. So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said, they said, the חכמים chachamim says to
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, הואיל וזו אשתו וזו אשתו, ho'il v'zo ishto
v'zo ishto,
since this one is his wife, the one that is נשואה, nesua,
and this one is his wife, the one that's an ארוסה, arusa,
זו מכרה בטל, zo machra batel, the same way when a woman
who is נשואה nesua tries to sell a property, it's void, אף
זו מכרה בטל, af zo machra batel, even if קידושין kiddushin it's
void. Okay, so it's very clear they wanted to say the sale
should be void even at the time of the קידושין. kiddushin. What?
Well, אשתו, ishto, it's not נשואתו, nesuato, but it's אשתו, ishto, okay?
It's really the same thing.
Well, no, it's not the same, that's the answer. But they wanted
to say once they're married, it shouldn't matter קידושין kiddushin or נשואין.
nisu'in. Okay. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said back to them, על
החדשים אנו בושים אלא שאתם מגלגלים עלינו את הישנים? al hachadashim anu
boshim ela she'atem megalgalim aleinu et hayeshanim? We are already embarrassed about
the recent properties, the ones she has at the time of נשואין,
nisu'in, and you want to extend this to the old properties, the
one from אירוסין? eirusin? No, no. There already it's different. שמע מינה
בדיעבד קאמר. Shma mina b'diavad ka'amar. You see that the rabbis are
trying to argue, the חכמים chachamim are trying to argue that even
בדיעבד b'diavad it should be void at the time of קידושין. kiddushin.
שמע מינה. Shma mina. That's a good point. Now we're going to
get to the actual debate about that. תניא, Tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי חנניה בן עקביא,
Amar Rabbi Chanania
ben Akavia, Hanina ben Akavia.
לא כך השיבם רבן גמליאל לחכמים. Lo kach heshivam Rabban Gamliel lachachamim.
That's not what he responded when they wanted to argue that it
should be void at the time of קידושין. kiddushin. He didn't just
give this answer about we're embarrassed, אנו בושים. anu boshim. There's a
more immediate like legal answer to that. אלא כך השיבם, Ela kach
heshivam, this was his response to them when they said it should
be void from the time of קידושין. kiddushin. לא, Lo, it's not
a good comparison, נשואין nisu'in from קידושין. kiddushin. אם אמרתם בנשואה, Im
amartem b'nesua,
why is it void when she tries to sell it as a
נשואה? nesua? שכן בעלה זכאי במציאתה ובמעשה ידיה ובהפרת נדריה. sheken ba'alah
zakai bimtzi'ata u'v'ma'aseh yadeha u'v'hafarat nedareha.
That's when the husband has a lot of legal rights to his
wife, to get the found property and the earnings of her hands
and he can annul her vows. And of course the most relevant
right he has is the פירות peirot of her property. So when
it's נשואה, nesua, he's got a lot of rights and therefore the
sale might be void. תאמרו בארוסה, Tomru b'arusa, would you say it
by ארוסה, arusa, שאין בעלה זכאי, she'ein ba'alah zakai, the husband doesn't
have rights, לא במציאתה ולא במעשה ידיה, lo bimtzi'ata v'lo b'ma'aseh yadeha,
not in things he finds, not in her earnings, ולא בהפרת נדריה,
v'lo b'hafarat nedareha, not to void her, annul her vows, although he
could do that together with the father, but not by himself. So
basically forget this אנו בושים anu boshim which seems to be like
a non-response, a non-responsive answer, right, it doesn't get to the core
of it. He's saying, no, when they were try to argue that
she couldn't sell it as an ארוסה, arusa, there's a much more
hard nail answer to that question. You know why she can, I
mean she can sell it as an ארוסה, arusa, because he has
no rights to her yet as an ארוסה. arusa. You're wrong. All
of his rights begin as a נשואה. nesua. They don't begin as
an ארוסה. arusa.
This is the קשיא kashya to the statement זו אשתו וזו אשתו.
zo ishto v'zo ishto.
Right. That's his response. It's not זו אשתו וזו אשתו. zo ishto
v'zo ishto. The truth, she's married in both cases, but it's a
very different legal status. Exactly.
ארוסתו. arusato. זו אשתו וזו ארוסתו.
zo ishto
v'zo arusato. Okay, or זו נשואתו וזו ארוסתו. zo nesuato v'zo arusato.
Anyway, okay,
ואמרו לו, v'amru lo, so they said back to him, רבי, Rabbi,
so this is they said רבי, Rabbi, they're talking to רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. מכרה עד שלא ניסת. Machra ad shelo niset.
Let's say a woman, so fine, you may be arguing the argument
that it should be totally valid if she sold it as ארוסה,
arusa, time of אירוסין, eirusin, because before נשואין nisu'in he has no
rights. Fine. I concede the point, yes, okay, let's concede the point.
If she sold it before the נשואין. nisu'in. Before the נשואין nisu'in
you say he has no rights, it should be totally valid. Fine,
I concede the point. But how about the following case? ניסת, Niset,
she had the property, then she got married, ואחר כך מכרה, v'achar
kach machra, and then she sold it, מהו? mahu? So she came
into the נשואין nisu'in with the property under her name. What would
be the story there? So this is the last part of the
משנה. mishna. She's trying to sell it after she's already a נשואה.
nesua. אמר להם, Amar lahem, so he said back to them, אף
זו מוכרת ונותנת וקיים. af zo mocheret v'notenet v'kayam.
Even this she can sell and it would be valid, because she
started with the property before the נשואין. nisu'in. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
so this is the... now that they challenge him with a much
stronger argument: הא לזוכה באשה, Ha lazacha be'isha,
now that she's already נשואין Nisuin and he has legal rights to
his wife, because that we said you concede that he has all
those legal rights at the time of נשואין, Nisuin, לא יזכה בנכסים,
lo yizke benchasim,
shouldn't he have rights to the property? So we concede the point
if she tries to sell it before the נשואין. Nisuin. But if
she sold it after the נשואין, Nisuin, even if she started with
the property earlier, that should be a case she shouldn't be able
to sell it. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he said back to them,
no, על חדשים אנו בושים אלא שאתם מגלגלין עלינו את הישנים. al
chadashim anu boshim ela she'atem megagelin alanu et hayeshanim. That's where he
gave the answer about being embarrassed, because there they actually had a
much stronger legal point, right? Once she's already נשואה, nesuah, what difference
does it make if it's new property or if it's property she
brought into the marriage? Either way right now she's a נשואה. nesuah.
And if one of the sales is void, the other sale should
be void and his answer was a little non-responsive. He says, oh,
we're already embarrassed about the case when she gets the new property,
it certainly isn't going to apply to the old property. Okay, but
what's the logic? What's the difference? Okay, so that's what רבי חנינא
בן עקביא Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya said. And this answer, we're embarrassed,
is a weaker answer and he only said it, he only said
it to the second question where they really had a stronger claim.
But the first point that it should be void even before נשואין,
Nisuin, there there's a very straightforward answer: before נשואין, Nisuin, he doesn't
have any rights.
Okay, so does he, I'm sorry for this, does he acquire the
title or just the פירות perot is his?
Just the פירות. perot.
So as long as someone's got title, yes,
that's
the stronger position, she can sell it.
So that's what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is saying is אנו בושים.
anu boshim. It's hard enough to explain why, why it's void in
any case.
Bottom line is she never loses title.
Okay, but however we explain why when it's, when it's new property
that the sale is void, why should it be different whether it's
new or it's old? Right now she's in the same legal relationship
with him. Right, so you can only make an emotional argument. Right,
so אנו בושים anu boshim does not really answer the question, it's
an emotional argument. But אנו בושים anu boshim reflects the idea that
it's hard to understand why any case should be void. She has
title. Right, that's, that's what אנו בושים anu boshim reflects. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so now the גמרא
Gemara wants to focus on the fact that in this ברייתא baraita
he said מוכרת ונותנת וקיים, mocheret venotenet vekayam,
that לכתחילה l'chatchila
she can sell and it's binding. And in the, in the משנה
Mishna he only said, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel only said that בדיעבד
bedi'avad if she sold it was binding. So the גמרא Gemara says
אנן תנן, anan tenan,
we taught in our משנה, Mishna, עד שלא ניסת וניסת, ad shelo
nisat venisat, if she had the property before the נשואין Nisuin and
now there's נשואין, Nisuin, רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban Gamliel omer, אם מכרה
ונתנה קיים, im machra venatna kayam, בדיעבד bedi'avad
if she sold it it's good. And this ברייתא baraita says לכתחילה
l'chatchila she can sell it, an even stronger opinion. אמר רב זביד,
Amar Rav Zevid, תני מוכרת ונותנת וקיים, tani mocheret venotenet vekayam, fine,
switch the language in our משנה. Mishna. Have it say that she
can do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. The problem, the problem is, by the
way, also because it's two versions of what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
said. The problem also is that it has him being more מיקל
meikel than בית הלל. Beit Hillel. בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's
clear that בית הלל Beit Hillel says לכתחילה l'chatchila she can't sell
it even at אירוסין, erusin, right? And here we have one version
that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says that even at נשואין Nisuin לכתחילה
l'chatchila she can sell it if she had it from before. So
one answer is just switch the text and have him say לכתחילה
l'chatchila in all the cases.
But מוכרת ונותנת mocheret venotenet means either she sells it or
gives it as a gift. Right, thank you, I wasn't explaining the
word נותנת. notenet. נותנת notenet means or as a gift, correct. She
can sell it or give it as a gift and it's binding.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're right, that's it. רב פפא אמר לא קשיא.
Rav Pappa amar lo kashya. No, it's, they're, it's true, it's a
debate between the משנה Mishna and the תוספתא Tosefta whether he can
do it לכתחילה l'chatchila and it's a debate. לא קשיא, lo kashya,
הא רבי יהודה אליבא דרבן גמליאל, ha Rabbi Yehuda aliba deRabban Gamliel,
הא רבי חנינא בן עקביא אליבא דרבן גמליאל. ha Rabbi Chanina ben
Akavya aliba deRabban Gamliel. In our משנה Mishna רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
was reporting this discussion of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the חכמים.
Chachamim. So according to רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda version of it, רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel only allowed it בדיעבד. bedi'avad. In the ברייתא baraita
it was רבי חנינא בן עקביא Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya that was
reporting the discussion, and in his version of it, רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel even allowed it לכתחילה, l'chatchila, even more lenient than בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, right?
בית הלל Beit Hillel wouldn't even allow it לכתחילה l'chatchila at אירוסין
erusin and according to this version רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel allowed it
לכתחילה l'chatchila at נשואין Nisuin as long as she, as long as
she came in with that property from before the נשואין. Nisuin. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי חנינא בן עקביא
כבית שמאי? Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya keBeit Shammai? So according to רבי
חנינא בן עקביא, Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is
going like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? And again בית שמאי Beit Shammai
only talked about אירוסין. erusin. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel according to him
is allowing it לכתחילה l'chatchila even at נשואין. Nisuin. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what he would
say: לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על דבר זה. lo nechlaku
Beit Shammai uBeit Hillel al davar zeh. He would claim that this
isn't even a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. According to his version רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel allowed it
to sell לכתחילה l'chatchila
and בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai would also
allow it to sell לכתחילה. l'chatchila. He disagrees with our משנה's Mishna
understanding of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay,
so according to one version following בית הלל Beit Hillel in our
משנה, Mishna, לכתחילה l'chatchila she can't sell it even at the time
of אירוסין erusin if she got it after the קידושין kiddushin took
place. And then, and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would then say and
also obviously לכתחילה l'chatchila she can't sell it at the נשואין, Nisuin,
that's obvious if she can't sell it at the time of אירוסין.
erusin.
But
And yeah, everybody and yeah לכתחילה l'chatchila yes.
And presumably ובית שמאי v'Beis Shammai would agree. And according to the
ברייתא, Braisa, רבי חנינא בן עקביא's Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya version of
it, everybody agrees, you know, that at the אירוסין eirusin לכתחילה l'chatchila
she can sell it. And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says that even
at the נישואין nisuin לכתחילה l'chatchila she can sell it if she
got it from before the נישואין. nisuin. Okay.
And בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel ve-Beit Shammai would they go...
They don't debate at all. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Then even at that point?
Yeah, presumably. Right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. רב ושמואל דאמרי
תרווייהו
Rav and Shmuel d'amri
tarvaihu now, so now if the way we would end it, the
idea that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina has completely they marginalized and רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel sort of had this moral voice of אנו בושים
anu boshim and the only time the husband could void the sale
would be if she got it after the נישואין. nisuin. But now
we're going to push back. Okay. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav and
Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say, בין שנפלו
נכסים עד שלא תתארס, bein shenafloo nechasim ad shelo tisarice, בין שנפלו
נכסים משתתארס ונישאת, bein shenafloo nechasim mishetisarice v'nisays,
whenever she had the property from, whether it was from before, even
before אירוסין eirusin when there was no husband on the scene at
all, she was five years old, or whether it was from before
נישואין, nisuin, I don't care how long she's had that property in
her name, now there's נישואין, nisuin, ונישאת, v'nisays, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות,
haba'al motzi miyad halekuchos,
the husband can now take the property out, so basically arguing in
the second case of our משנה Mishna that after the נישואין nisuin
against רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. Once there's נישואין, nisuin, it doesn't matter
where the property is coming from, once there's נישואין, nisuin, he has
rights to that property and therefore he can stop the sale in
either case.
It's like saying, it's like
saying if the woman, the girl makes the sale, once a husband
comes into the picture, that sale is restructured as if it were
a loan.
No, no, no, we're not retroactively changing anything.
But why? The sale was a good sale when it was made.
No, no, no, she got the property before there was a husband,
right? She inherited it, she won the lottery, whatever she did. Anything
she does before נישואין nisuin is completely binding. What רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel are saying is, now she still has that property in
her name, now there's נישואין, nisuin, okay. So all they're arguing on
is the last case of the משנה. Mishna. They're basically siding with
the חכמים hachachamim against רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and they're saying that
once there's נישואין, nisuin, any sale she'll try to do now is
void, no matter when the property came.
אנו מקח טעות. Anu mekach tovo.
אנו מקח טעות, Anu mekach tovo, he has rights to it, right?
I mean, from the perspective of the purchaser, yeah, right. Okay. It's
like somebody sold you something that they weren't entitled to sell, right?
Sold you the Brooklyn Bridge. Okay. So all right. Yeah, anyway, right.
It's a bargain. That's my... There's a joke, the one joke I
got about that is guy says, okay, I'll sell you the Brooklyn
Bridge. And guy says for a million dollars. He says a million
dollars, says great. So he takes out his wallet, he takes out
his checkbook and he says, you got a pen? Give him a
pen, writes a million dollars, tears off the check, gives it to
him, walks away. His friend says to him, I don't understand, you
just bought a bridge that he didn't, doesn't own with money you
don't have. So he said, what? And this pen is nothing?
So anyway, alright. So moving
on. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So רב ושמואל
דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav and Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu, so רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו,
Rav and Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu, where am I? הבעל
מוציא מיד הלקוחות,
haba'al motzi
miyad
halekuchos, רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav and Shmuel d'amri tarvaihu, בין שנפלו
נכסים עד שלא תתארס, bein shenafloo nechasim ad shelo tisarice, בין שנפלו
נכסים משתתארס ונישאת, bein shenafloo nechasim mishetisarice v'nisays, now there's נישואין, nisuin,
I don't care when she had the property, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות.
haba'al motzi miyad halekuchos. The husband can take out the property, the
sale is void, basically ruling in the last case of our משנה
Mishna like the חכמים hachachamim against רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. כמאן? K'man?
Who is this going like? דלא כרבי יהודה, de'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda, דלא
כרבי חנינא בן עקביא. de'lo k'Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya. Not like רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda version who said, okay, לכתחילה l'chatchila not but בדיעבד
bedieved it's good. Not like רבי חנינא בן עקביא's Rabbi Chanina ben
Akavya version of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who said that even לכתחילה
l'chatchila she can do it. So who you going like? And presumably
it assumes you can't just say we're going like the חכמים hachachamim
because the whole way the משנה Mishna is structured is that רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel completely silenced the חכמים. hachachamim. The חכמים hachachamim don't
seem to be a viable position by the time you're done with
the משנה Mishna or the ברייתא. Braisa. So who is a viable
position that would still say it's not valid? So the גמרא Gemara
says, who is this going like? אינהו דאמרי כרבותינו. Innu d'amri k'rabboseinu.
They say like the רבותינו. rabboseinu. Who are the רבותינו? rabboseinu? Those
are different than the חכמים. hachachamim. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Braisa, רבותינו חזרו ונמנו. rabboseinu chazru v'nimnu. So the תוספתא Tosefta
says after רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says it's valid if she had
it as old property, רבותינו rabboseinu got back together and took another
vote and they said, בין שנפלו עד שלא תתארס ובין שנפלו משתתארס
ונישאת, bein shenafloo ad shelo tisarice ubein shenafloo mishetisarice v'nisays, whether it
was from before the קידושין, kiddushin, whether it was after the קידושין,
kiddushin, now there's נישואין, nisuin, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות. haba'al motzi miyad
halekuchos. The husband can void it. Okay, it's quite interesting, right? You
can sort of see the dynamics, like somebody there and is making
like this moral argument. He's like... shaming everybody into silence. It's like
saying, you should be embarrassed about even voiding it in the first
place, how can you even think about saying that he should be
able to void it when she got the property? So everybody is
shamed into silence because he's telling us we all should be embarrassed
like why do we even have a right? So but then afterwards,
after he goes away,
we're going to sit back again and we're going to take a
new vote and we're all going to decide, you know what, it
makes sense in this case or
whatever. Yeah, but maybe they could have done it because maybe they
thought it'd just be better for the family? Oh yeah, well why
did they do it? Look, that gets to the question about why
he could void it even when, even, why they were embarrassed about
the most basic case, about the new property? Because what's the legal
right there to void the sale? If he has title to it,
why could they void the sale? So there must have been some
assumption and this we're going to see in a minute, that because
of basically the financial realities there were some, again I can't, I
don't fully understand the economics or whatever but there was some logic
that that was in order to make the husband's position more firm
in order that he could invest the property more, be more certain,
whatever the reasons are that they gave him the פירות, peirot, because
if he's providing for her he has to have certain types of
financial rights and entitlements as well it made sense to not make
it an avenue for her to be able to sell the property
out from under him. And once they felt that that was appropriate,
then the same way it would be appropriate for new property it
could be just as appropriate for old property. Okay, but Michael is
correct, meaning the logic that he could void the sale it's clear
it
does not naturally emerge from his rights. It seems and that's why
they said they were embarrassed about it which shows that there was
some type of a proactive enactment that allowed him to void the
sale and that probably had to do more with policy issues than
legal rights issues, because of certain policy considerations we gave him the
power to block the sale. And then the question is okay, so
how far should we extend that? And then it becomes almost like
a policy debate and you can say this is, we're embarrassed enough
about the first thing because we're encroaching on her on her legal
rights. All right, but anyway, but that's where it ended up that
after he sort of stepped off the scene they did say that
once there's נשואין nissuin he can void the sale regardless. Okay let's
take a look let's do a little bit more. משניסת mishe-niset אלו
ואלו מודים eilu va-eilu modim
once there is נשואין nissuin בית הלל Beis Hillel ובית שמאי v'Beis
Shammai agree right that the משנה mishnah said that oh if she
got the property after נשואין nissuin then that's the case everybody agrees.
Everybody agrees that if she got the property after נשואין nissuin it's
void if she tries to sell it. So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא תנינא לתקנת אושא, leima tenina le-takkanat Usha,
let's say our משנה mishnah is teaching us the תקנת אושא, takkanat
Usha, the תקנה takkanah that they made at אושא. Usha. What was
the תקנה takkanah they made at אושא? Usha? דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא באושא התקינו de-amar Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Chanina be-Usha hitkinu האשה שמכרה
בנכסי מלוג בחיי בעלה ha-ishah she-machrah be-nichsei milog be-chayei ba'alah
in אושא Usha they established and here we do see it was
an enactment and it was not like a natural legal right that
if a woman tried to sell her property her נכסי מלוג nichsei
milog while the husband was alive ומתה ve-metah and then she dies
and so if she had not sold it the husband would inherit
her right and but now she did sell it הבעל מוציא מיד
הלקוחות ha-ba'al motzi mi-yad ha-lakochot the husband can now take it from
the hand of the purchasers and void the sale and say I'm
the rightful heir of my wife she wasn't able to sell it.
So this seems to be exactly what our משנה mishnah said right
the woman is trying to sell her נכסי מלוג nichsei milog the
husband can void it. So the גמרא Gemara is now actually saying
how is this different than תקנת אושא? takkanat Usha? Isn't that exactly
תקנת אושא? takkanat Usha? And presumably תקנת אושא takkanat Usha actually was
a later תקנה. takkanah. So how is our משנה mishnah any different?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the
גמרא Gemara says מתניתין בחייה לפירות. matnitin be-chayeha le-peirot.
Our משנה mishnah where it says the husband can void it is
when she tried to sell, it's during her life and what she
tried to sell away was the right to the fruit. So she
tried to sell away what the husband actually has rights to okay
and that's why our משנה mishnah was clear that that she can't
sell away because he's got rights to the פירות. peirot. Okay so
he can't sell to somebody else. תקנת אושא takkanat Usha by תקנת
אושא takkanat Usha it was giving the husband even more rights בגופו
של קרקע be-gufo shel karka that she can't even sell the title
to it ואחר מיתה ve-achar mitah and after she dies right what's
why does he care who has the title? He cares who has
the title because if she dies he would inherit her and if
she sold away the title he won't inherit her. So אושא Usha
prevented her from selling the title to basically cut away his opportunity
to inherit this property. Okay now that's a real חידוש chiddush why
should he be able to stop the title? But what you see
that the גמרא Gemara is doing is it's claiming because I actually
thought that that was פשט peshat in the משנה. mishnah. I think
פשט peshat of the משנה mishnah sounds like she's trying to sell
the title. Exactly. But what the גמרא Gemara is doing to distinguish
it from תקנת אושא takkanat Usha is saying that the פשט peshat
in the משנה mishnah is that she's not trying to sell the
title she's just trying to sell away the right to the fruit.
But if that's all she's trying to do then now we go
back and say actually we understand why she shouldn't be able to
do it. Once there's נשואין nissuin and he has rights to the
fruit how could she sell it away? So what's the logic of
course he It might be a difference between who owns the fruits
or who's like entitled to it, like do you imagine that he
owns the field and the fruits are hers? But once she gets
them, then she has to give it to him the same way
he has to pay for her food, she has to give him
money that she earned from the field, but it's still her earning,
she just has to give it to him. If it's still her
earning and she gives it to him, then she could sell it
to somebody else, whereas if fundamentally he can void the sale, that
means it's not her earning, it's his earnings. Do you understand? So
it seems the way the גמרא's Gemara trying to frame this, if
we're going on the משנה Mishnah trying to sell the fruit, the
only way there could be a debate there is how do you
conceptualize his right to the income. Is it basically she earns the
money and then gives it to him, then maybe she could sell
it, or is it that she never earns it, he earns it
and then obviously she can't sell it?
Okay, and the second אושא Usha has now thrown us back to
reread the entire סוגיא sugya as alternative?
Exactly. Based on this, now we go back and read everything about
the fruit, which is what I mentioned at the time of the
משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
I guess we will end here because the next part ties in
anyway, so we'll do the next דף. daf. Let's, alright fine, we'll
do the next דף. daf. ורבן שמעון חולק בנכסים. V'Rabban Shimon cholek
b'nechasim. Rabban Shimon
distinguishes between property the husband knows about and doesn't know about. אלו
הן ידועין ואלו הן שאינן ידועין? Elu hen yeduin v'elu hen she'einan
yeduin? What is property he knows and what is property he doesn't
know? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, ידועין
מקרקעי, yeduin mekarkaei, things he knows about is land because land you
can't hide away. שאינן ידועין, She'einan yeduin, things he doesn't know about,
is מטלטלין, metaltelin, chattel, even though he knows about it, at least
it's in a legal category of stuff that is presumably able to
be not known about, able to be hidden away, and that one
he can't stop. ורבי יוחנן אמר אלו ואלו ידועין. V'Rabbi Yochanan amar
elu v'elu yeduin. No, either one he could know about. ואלו הן
שאינן ידועין, V'elu hen she'einan yeduin, the following is stuff he doesn't
know that he's not entitled to block the sale: כל שיושבת כאן
ונפלו לה נכסים במדינת הים, kol she'yosheves kan v'naflu lah nechasim b'medinas
hayam, that the property is in some faraway place. Of course, go
ahead and define, even though it's קרקע, karka, go ahead and define
faraway place. What's faraway place? Next city, next state, next country, how
many miles?
New Jersey to New York?
I don't know, exactly. Right.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya
nami hachi, we taught similarly, אלו הן שאינן ידועין כל שיושבת כאן
ונפלו לה נכסים במדינת הים. elu hen she'einan yeduin kol she'yosheves kan
v'naflu lah nechasim b'medinas hayam. Now, why does that matter that, I'll
just read one last רש"י, Rashi, why should he not, why should
it matter whether he knows about it or doesn't know about it?
So just look at this little
רש"י, Rashi, ידועין מקרקעי, yeduin mekarkaei, the like second to wide line
before the, second to last of the narrow lines, על מנת אותן
נכסים נשאה. al menas osan nechasim nesaha. If he knew about it,
see Joe, then when there was the נשואין, nisuin, he was expecting
the, you know, that money. לפיכך מכרה בטל שהיה מצפה,
L'fichach michrah
batel she'hayah metzapeh, we're
rewarding gold diggers.
Now, שהיה מצפה שתפול לה אותה ירושה, she'hayah metzapeh she'tipol lah osah
yerushah, he felt that he had rights and he was expecting it,
it was with that understanding. If it's stuff he didn't know about,
so it's interesting, presumably he's still entitled to the פירות, peiros, but
his rights are not so great that he can say that he
can legally say that the sale should be void. Okay, we're not,
you know, he still gets the פירות peiros from that, that is
his legal right, but you can't say you knew about it, you
expected it, and therefore you're entitled to say to prevent the sale
from going through. Alright, we'll pick up with this tomorrow.
The children inherit the father, but they don't inherit the mother's? Correct.